Finding Aid for Sligh Family Papers 1842-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sligh Family Papers
1842-2012
Sligh family.
85481 AC UAl Aa 2
Grand Rapids, Michigan family, involved in furniture making and other businesses, also active in local state and Republican Party politics and businessmen's associations. Papers include family papers and correspondence, business records, scrapbooks and visual materials.
36 linear feet in 41 boxes
31 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Sligh family collection has come to the library in several accessions beginning in 1958, as the gift of Charles R. Sligh, Jr. (donor no. 3474 ) and his family.
The collection is open for research.
The Sligh family of Grand Rapids, Michigan have been prominent businessmen and furniture makers for over one hundred years. The first generation of Slighs to come to western Michigan was James W. Sligh (1821-1963) who was a clothier and not a furniture maker. Immigrating from Scotland to Canada in 1833, and from there to Rochester, New York, in 1838, James W. Sligh finally settled in Grand Rapids in 1848. When civil war broke out, he entered service as captain with Company F, 1st Michigan Engineers and Mechanics. He died November 15, 1863, from injuries received from a train derailed by Confederate guerrillas.
Though still a boy at the time of his father's death Charles R. Sligh (1850-1927) worked to help support his family. Following a series of odd jobs, Sligh was apprenticed for four years to a local tinsmith. He clerked for one year at the Foster and Stevens Hardware Store, and then in 1875, he went to work in the finishing room of Berkey and Gay, Grand Rapids furniture manufacturers. He was soon promoted to foreman of the finishing department and then became one of the salesmen for the company. Sligh was probably the first furniture salesman to make extensive use of photographs in his sales presentations. Up until that time, salesmen usually followed carloads of their companies' furniture into various cities along the train route. From the railroad yards, they would call the local dealers down to examine their wares, and sales would be made directly from the train. Using photographs enabled Sligh to open up new markets without being tied to the railroad.
On February 24, 1880, Sligh and his brother-in-law Lewis Hawkins organized the Sligh Furniture Company. With Sligh as president and chief salesman, the company prospered and grew. In the 1890s, with bicycling a new and popular fad, Sligh attempted to diversify his company to include the manufacture of bicycle wheels. This venture proved a failure, and thereafter, Sligh devoted most of his business energies to furniture manufacturing in general and the Sligh Company in particular. He developed new sources for the mahogany needed in his production by organizing a company which cut lumber in Honduras and then transported it to Grand Rapids. He established an agency in England for the sale of his furniture. He was president of the National Furniture Manufacturers Association (1888-1892), and was for many years president of the Grand Rapids Furniture Manufacturers Association. And in 1900, when his supply of mirror glass was restricted by a cartel of French, German, and Belgian manufacturers, Sligh traveled to Europe and sought out a supply of glass from a number of small, independent Belgian manufacturers.
With his company well established, Sligh began to devote more of his time and effort to politics and public service. He was a member of the Grand Rapids Board of Education in 1882 and 1883, and was active in local Republican politics. In 1895, Sligh split with his party over the question of bimetallism. He advocated free silver and was one of the organizers of the Silver Republican Party in Michigan. In 1896, he was nominated by the Free Silver Republicans, the Democrats, and the Populists to be the fusion candidate for governor. He was defeated in this election by Hazen Pingree. In 1906, Sligh ran unsuccessfully for mayor of Grand Rapids. In 1912, Governor Chase S. Osborn appointed him to the state's Workmen's Compensation Commission; and in 1915, he was made a member of the Grand Rapids Charter Commission which drafted that city's charter. Sligh was elected state senator for his district in 1922, and in 1924, he ran unsuccessfully in the Republican gubernatorial primary.
Sligh was also involved in local philanthropic pursuits, including the Boy Scouts, the YMCA, and the planning for a proposed (but never completed) Sligh Memorial Hospital for Children. Among other business interests, Sligh was president of the Santiam Land and Timber Co., president of the Clark-Sligh Timber Co., and secretary-treasurer of the Clark Iron Co., which had large holdings of mineral lands in the Mesabi Range. Sligh died September 15, 1927.
With his death and worsening business conditions in the furniture industry, the Sligh Furniture Company floundered and failed. Its assets were liquidated in 1932. Charles R. Sligh, Jr. (1906- ) who had gained experience in his father's business, was forced to begin anew a business which would have the family name. In 1933, this Sligh together with O.W. Lowry, who had been the company's superintendent, pooled their resources to purchase an idle furniture factory in Holland, Michigan. The Charles R. Sligh Company gradually grew. In 1940, the two men opened another plant (the Sligh-Lowry Company) in Zeeland, Michigan. This was followed in 1945 by a third company, the Grand Rapids Chair Company, then by a fourth, the Sligh Furniture Showrooms in New York City.
Charles R. Sligh, Jr., like his father, was concerned with national economic issues. As a skilled debater, he became a spokesman first for the furniture industry and then for all of American business through his work with the NAM, the National Association of Manufacturers. Sligh was chairman of the NAM's taxation committee, and in 1952 was vice president of the NAM's Michigan-Ohio region. He was elected president of the NAM in December 1952, and after his term expired in December 1953, he was elected chairman of the NAM Executive Board. In April 1957, he was elected chief administrative officer and executive vice president of the organization. While with NAM, Sligh gained fame as spokesman for the business point of view in a series of debates with labor leaders, notably George Meany and Walter Reuther.
Though a Republican like his father, Charles Sligh Jr. never ran for high public office, preferring instead to express his political views through his NAM activities. He did serve as chairman of the Kent County Republican Party in 1952 and was an acquaintance of many national Republican leaders.
Robert Lewis Sligh (1928-2012), was Charles Jr.' son. Robert "Bob" Sligh got his first job as a hand sander at the Baker Furniture, Inc. in Holland, Mich. in 1945 at the age of 17. In 1946 he enrolled in the Furniture Course at the University of Michigan, a course established by Charles R. Sligh Jr. and Chuck Kindel of Kindel Furniture. The course was headquartered in the Wood Technology Department of the Forestry School. Robert Sligh graduated with a B.S. in Wood Technology in 1949, followed by a summer at Wright-Peterson Air Force Base in Dayton, Ohio, becoming a Reserve Air Force officer. Robert Sligh served with the 32nd Air Division Defense as Officer in Charge of Intelligence Flight. In 1954 he was released from active duty and joined the Sligh-Lowry as Assistant to the Sales Manager. Two years later he was promoted to Sales Manager of Sligh-Lowry reporting to Bill Lowry, the Vice President. He became the Sligh Company's President in 1968 and continued in this capacity until 1990.
The Sligh family collection has come to the library in several accessions beginning in 1958, with significant accessions acquired in 1981 and 2013. Material located in Boxes 23-24 was acquired with the 1981 accession. Material located in Boxes 29-41 came to the library in 2013. The Sligh family papers are organized in seven major series:
James W. Sligh papers, 1842-1865 (Box 1)
Charles R. Sligh Sr. papers, 1866-1927 (Boxes 2-10, 24)
Charles R. Sligh Jr. papers, 1928-1969 (Boxes 11-18, 23-24, 32-33)
Robert L. Sligh papers, 1945-1946, 1988 and undated (Box 33)
Sligh Family Business Records (Boxes 18-20, 29-32)
Newspaper Clippings and Scrapbooks Clippings (Boxes 20-22) Scrapbooks (Outsize volumes and Boxes 38-41)
Visual Materials Photographs (Box 25) Films (Boxes 26-27)
The Sligh family collection consists of the personal and business papers of the four generations of Slighs mentioned in the biographical introduction: James W. Sligh, Charles R. Sligh, Charles R. Sligh, Jr., and Robert L. Sligh. Although there is some overlap, the files have been arranged into seven series, one for each of these three Slighs, one for the Sligh Furniture Company and related family businesses, and one each for Newspaper clippings and Scrapbooks, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
American Federation of Labor.; California Land and Water Company.; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); Corporations.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Elections--Michigan--1896.; Elections--Michigan--1902.; Elections--Michigan--1904.; Elections--Michigan--1912.; Elections--Michigan--1922.; Elections--Michigan--1924.; Lumber trade--Michigan.; Lumbering--Michigan.; Eugenics.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; Ford Motor Company.; Furniture industry and trade--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Grand River (Mich.); Groesbeck, Alexander J. (Alexander Joseph), 1873-1953.; United States--Emigration and immigration.; Furniture workers--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Lakeview Oil Company.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1907-1908); Michigan. Legislature. Senate.; Michigan. State Highway Dept.; Michigan State University.; Michigan Society for Crippled Children.; Michigan School of Religion.; Musgrave, Richard A. (Richard Abel), 1910-2007; National Association of Manufacturers (U.S.); United States. Army. Michigan Engineers and Mechanics Regiment, 1st (1861-1865). Company F.; National Security League.; Patton, John, 1850-1907.; Philippines--History--Philippine American War, 1899-1902.; Prohibition--United States.; Railroads--United States.; Republican Party (Mich.); Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970.; International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft and Agricultural Implement Workers of America.; Michigan--Politics and government--1877-1898.; Michigan--Politics and government--1899-1916.; Michigan--Politics and government--1917-1921.; Michigan--Politics and government--1922-1928.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Singer Sewing Machine Company.; Sligh family.; Squier, George Owen, 1865-1934.; Taxation--United States.; Voyages and travels.; Travelers.; World War, 1914-1918.; Workers' compensation.; Silver question.; Immigrants--United States.
Contributors:
Abbott, Sidney D., b. 1826.; Alger, R. A. (Russell Alexander), 1836-1907.; Baker, Frederick A., b. 1846.; Bliss, Aaron Thomas, 1837-1906.; Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Burrows, Julius C. (Julius Caesar), 1837-1915.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Cavanaugh, Martin J., 1866-; Cudney, Charles H., 1828-1904.; Curtis, William Eleroy, 1850-1911.; Cutcheon, Byron M., 1836-1908.; Drake, Richard L.; Emery, John Garfield, 1881-; Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928.; Ferry, Thomas White, 1827-1896.; Foote, Mark, 1882-1957.; Geerlings, Clyde H., 1904-; Gifford, Edson P., b. 1832.; Goodspeed, Richard D.; Grand Army of the Republic.; Hannah, John A., 1902-1991; Holden, Ebenezer G. D., 1845-1912.; Hopkins, Enos, 1821-1896.; Hopkins, Samuel W., b. 1845.; Innes, William Powers, 1826-1893.; Jewell, David A., b. 1828.; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944.; Lighthall, Dow L., b. 1809.; Luce, Cyrus Gray, 1824-1905.; McGill, Charles William, 1865-; McGrath, John W., b. 1837.; McMillan, James, 1838-1902.; Mantle, Lee, 1851-1934.; Meany, George, 1894-1980.; Miller, Clement F., b. 1830.; Morgenthau, Henry, 1856-1946.; Morse, Allen Benton, 1839-1921.; Nevins, William S., b. 1829.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Pingree, Hazen S., 1840-1901.; Rich, John Treadway, 1841-1926.; Richardson, George F., 1850-1923.; Sligh, Charles Robert, 1850-1927.; Sligh, Charles R., Jr. (Charles Robert), 1906-1997; Sligh, James May, 1844-1921.; Sligh, James Wilson, 1821-1863.; Sligh, Mary Stowell Conger, 1854-1903.; Sligh, Robert Burns, 1856-1879.; Sligh, Robert Lewis, 1928-2012.; Sly, Alexander C., 1863-; Smith, William Alden, 1859-1932.; Stockbridge, Mr. (Francis Brown), 1826-1894.; Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.; Turner, James Munroe, 1850-1896.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Walker, George D., 1820-1863.; Warner, Frederick Maltby, 1865-1923.; Warner, Walter, b. 1816.; Watkins, Charles W., b. 1844.; Watkins, Erwin C., b. 1839.; Wells, Albert, b. 1835.; Wheeler, Frederick, 1862-; White, George W., b. 1828.; Whiting, Justin Rice, 1847-1903.
Visual Materials - Subjects
Broadcasting.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Furniture.; Furniture industry--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Industrial buildings--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Military training.; National Association of Manufacturers (U.S.); Photographs.; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970.; Sligh, Charles Robert, 1850-1927.; Sligh, Charles R., Jr. (Charles Robert), 1906-1997; Sligh, James Wilson, 1821-1863.; Sligh Furniture Company.; Soldiers--American.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Water skiing.; World War, 1914-1918.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- James W. Sligh papers
  The first series covers the period 1842-1865 and largely concerns the activities of James W. Sligh, though there is also a mixture of his son's papers (James M. Sligh), particularly during the period of the Civil War. The files have been arranged into three subseries: correspondence, business receipts and related materials, and bound records, principally daybooks and account books, and Civil War diaries. The correspondence for the 1860s includes the letters written by James W. and James M. Sligh when they served with the 1st Michigan Engineers and Mechanics as well as scattered letters which were written by the following men: Sidney Abbot, Charles Cudney, Edson Gifford, Enos Hopkins, William Innes, David Jewell, Don Lighthall, John McGrath, Clement Miller, William Nevins, George Walker, Walder Warner, Albert Wells, and George White.
  - Biographical Information
    - Genealogical and biographical data (Box 1)
    - Sligh family genealogy (Box 1)
    - Horoscopes (Box 1)
    - Civil War citations and awards (Box 28)
    - Civil War muster roll, 1863 (Folder UA1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1845-1850 (Box 1)
    - 1851-1855 (Box 1)
    - 1856-1860 (Box 1)
    - 1861 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1862 (Box 1)
    - April-June 1862 (Box 1)
    - July-September 1862 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1862 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1863 (Box 1)
    - April-June 1863 (Box 1)
    - July-September 1863 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1863 (Box 1)
    - 1864 (Box 1)
    - 1865 (Box 1)
  - Papers (largely business records)
    - 1842-1850, undated (Box 1)
    - 1851 (Box 1)
    - 1852 (Box 1)
    - 1853 (Box 1)
    - 1854-1855 (Box 1)
    - 1856-1859 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1860 (Box 1)
    - April-June 1860 (Box 1)
    - July-September 1860 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1860 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1861 (Box 1)
    - April-June 1861 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1861 (Box 1)
    - 1862-1865 (Box 1)
  - Bound records of James W. Sligh
    - Daybook (Box 1)
      - 1848-1852 (Box 1)
      - 1852-1860 (Volume AC)
      - 1860-1861 (Box 1)
      - 1860-1865 (Box 1)
      - 1849-1865 (Box 1)
    - Account book, 1828-1845 (Box 1)
    - Account book, circa 1840s-1861 (Box 1)
    - Diaries
      - 1860 (Box 1)
      - 1862, 2 volumes (Box 1)
      - 1863 (Box 1)
    - Notebooks, 6 volumes (Box 1)
      (including Masonic memorandum books)
- Charles R. Sligh, Sr. papers
  The second series covers the period 1866-1927 and centers around the career of Charles R. Sligh, though the early folders do have papers relating to his brothers, James M. Sligh and Robert Burns Sligh, and their mother Eliza Wilson Sligh, and Charles R. Sligh's first wife, Mary Stowell Sligh and her family. The bulk of this series, however, relates to the business and political activities of Charles R. Sligh. There are three subseries here, consisting of correspondence, business and political materials, and bound records, principally political scrapbooks, business and land records, personal account books and diaries, and a volume written by Sligh containing a combination family history and autobiography. Among the topics covered in this series are the Grand River improvement scheme (1889-1905); the furniture industry (especially 1887-1890, 1911, and 1926); the Grand Rapids mayoralty election of 1906; the state constitutional convention in 1907; the election of 1912; World War I, including the preparedness movement, the Plattsburg Training Camp, the National Security League, and airplane production; Sligh's election to and activities in the Michigan State Senate, 1922-1924; the gubernatorial primary election of 1924; and miscellaneous business investments in California and Arizona, especially in the California Land and Water Co., the Lakeview Oil Co., the Interstate Oil Co. of California, and a variety of Arizona irrigation and land companies (1920-1927).
  Correspondents represented in this series include Russell A. Alger; Thomas W. Ferry; Francis B. Stockbridge; James McMillan; George Richardson; William Jennings Bryan; John T. Rich; Byron M. Cutcheon; Cyrus G. Luce; Aaron T. Bliss; Hazen S. Pingree; William E. Curtis; James M. Turner; William Alden Smith; Julius C. Burrows; Samuel W. Hopkins; Charles W. Watkins; Ebenezer Holden; Justin R. Whiting; Allen B. Morse; Erwin C. Watkins; Alexander C. Sly; Charles A. Towne; George F. Richardson; Fred A. Baker; Lee Mantle; D.A. Reynolds; Woodbridge Ferris; Fred Warner; Martin J. Cavanaugh; Chase S. Osborn; Frank Knox; Richard L. Drake; William P. Belden; Henry Morgenthau, Sr.; Arthur H. Vandenberg; Mark Foote; Frederick Wheeler; Marion L. Burton; Wilbur M. Brucker and John G. Emery.
  - Correspondence
    - 1866-1910, 58 folders (Box 2)
    - 1911-September 1918, 51 folders (Box 3)
    - October 1918-January 1923, 48 folders (Box 4)
    - February 1923-1927, 40 folders (Box 5)
  - Papers (largely business and political materials)
    - circa 1866-1927 (Box 6)
    - 1866-1896, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - 1894-1897, 2 folders (Box 6)
      (printed materials relating to bimetallism)
    - 1897-1917, 20 folders (Box 6)
    - 1916-1917 (Box 6)
      (printed materials concerning preparedness)
    - 1918-1921, 17 folders (Box 6)
    - 1922-1923, 6 folders (Box 7)
    - 1924, undated, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - January 1924-April 1924, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - April 1924 (Box 7)
      (nominating petitions)
    - May 1924-1926, 10 folders (Box 7)
    - 1926 (Box 7)
      (directory of American furniture companies on 3x5 cards)
    - 1927, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
      (dates vary)
    - Grand River Improvement Project, circa 1890-1903; 8 folders (Box 24)
  - Oil Company Reports
    - Reports of Interstate Oil Company (Box 7)
    - Reports of Lake View No. 2 Oil Company (Box 7)
  - Bound records of Charles R. Sligh
    - Business letterbook, 1908-1909 (Box 8)
    - Business and land records, 6 volumes (Box 8)
    - Business and land records, 2 volumes (Box 9)
    - Scrapbooks of gubernatorial campaign, 1924; 2 volumes (Box 9)
    - Personal scrapbook, 1880-1903 (Box 10)
    - Family history-autobiography (Box 10)
    - Personal account books and diaries (Box 10)
- Charles R. Sligh, Jr. papers
  The third series of the Sligh papers largely concerns the interests of Charles R. Sligh, Jr. (1928-1967) There is early scattered material, approximately 1928-1939, concerning the estate of his father, but the bulk of the materials covers the 1940s and 1950s, and relates to his involvement in the National Association of Manufacturers and his interest in national economic policy. There are several subseries, including correspondence, papers, speeches, audio-tapes and phonograph records of NAM speeches and programs, and bound records, including scrapbooks concerning his furniture business, his NAM activities, and his interest in water-skiing, and personal financial ledgers. Correspondents in this series include Clyde H. Geerlings, John A. Hannah, George Meany, and Arthur H. Summerfield.
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 32)
    - 1901-1902 (Box 32)
    - 1903-1909, 7 folders (Box 32)
    - 1910 (Box 33)
    - 1913 (Box 33)
    - 1915 (Box 33)
    - 1918-1919, 2 folders (Box 33)
    - 1923-1925, 3 folders (Box 33)
    - 1928-1940, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - (Christmas cards), 1933-1943 (Box 33)
    - 1940 (Box 33)
    - 1942 (Box 33)
    - 1948 (Box 33)
    - World War II letters (Box 11)
    - July 1951-1953, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Letters of congratulations upon election as president of the National Association of Manufacturers, December 1952 (Box 11)
    - Letters of appreciation upon completion of his term as N.A.M. president (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1955, largely concerning debates with George Meany and Walter Reuther, December 1953-January 1954; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - 1954-1967, 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Notes and Articles
    - Notes of meetings with President Eisenhower and other public officials, 1953 (Box 11)
    - Articles (Box 11)
  - Day Books, 1945-1953; 1955-1969 (Box 33)
  - Diaries, 1921; 1933 (Box 33)
  - Speeches and public appearances
    - 1950-May 1953, 12 folders (Box 11)
    - June 1953-1954, 7 folders (Box 12)
    - circa 1953 (Box 12)
      (miscellaneous)
    - 1954-1964, 8 folders (Box 12)
    - "Christianity in Business" (Box 12)
    - Itineraries, 3 folders (Box 24)
    - Presentation on John F. Kennedy (Box 24)
    - Broadcasts and interviews (Box 24)
    - Speaking engagements, 6 folders (Box 24)
    - Speaking engagements refund (Box 24)
    - Conference of National Organization, 6 folders (Box 24)
    - National Industrial Conference Board (Box 24)
    - Congress of American Industry
      - 1953 (Box 24)
      - 1954 (Box 24)
    - Second International Conference (Paris, 1954) (Box 24)
  - Papers (largely business materials)
    - 1928-1942, 13 folders (Box 12)
  - Papers (largely concerning National Association of Manufacturers)
    - July 1951-May 1952, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - 1953 (Box 12)
      (Itinerary)
    - January-June 1953, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - May-June 1953 (Box 12)
      (European trip)
    - July-December 1953 (Box 12)
    - 1954 (Box 12)
    - May 1954, 2 folders (Box 12)
      (2nd International Conference of Manufacturers)
    - 1955, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 13)
      (debates with George Meany)
    - 1956-1977, 6 folders (Box 13)
    - National Association of Manufacturers miscellanea (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 13)
  - Publications
    - "Invest in America" (Box 33)
    - "Keep the Promise of Tomorrow" (Box 33)
    - "Westward Bound....the diary of a furniture salesman" (Box 33)
    - "What Management Expects of Organized Labor" (Box 33)
    - "Why Our Nation Needs a Flat-Rate Manufacturers Tax" (Box 33)
  - Scrapbooks
    (dismantled and put into folders)
    The scrapbooks largely concern C.S., Jr.'s work with the N.A.M.
    - Scrapbook no. 1
      (unbound)
      - Clippings, 1951 (Box 13)
        concerning appearance before Senate Finance Committee, July 5, 1951